[SPEAKER_00]: So, when I was speaking about virtue and the mind, something I had thought of bringing up is, why is it that, this is to say, that virtue is a necessary precondition, like purification of virtue, not just some amount of virtue, but purification of virtue is a precondition for purification of citta, which is a precondition for purification of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is it that you can't just take a random person off of the street and then tell them to abandon the five hindrances and purify their citta?
[SPEAKER_00]: Just by telling them to do exactly what the Buddha said in the suttas, just to abandon greed and aversion in regard to the world, abandon covetousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why wouldn't they be able to do that?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because acting in certain ways, whether you recognize it or not, is accepting that.
[SPEAKER_05]: But what will happen if, let's say, at that moment, they're not acting in any unwholesome way?
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, for that moment, factually, they're kind of... they're not breaking any precepts, because they're sitting down in a room, not doing anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they're kind of in seclusion at that moment.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why would they fail?
[SPEAKER_03]: Do they lack a degree of self-transparency?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but that would be like a very broad... that wouldn't necessarily tell you, like, what do I do then?
[SPEAKER_00]: How can I fix that?
[SPEAKER_02]: You'd still be looking at objects, at stuff, at things that arise, and blaming them, or trying to solve the problem by replacing, getting more or less.
[SPEAKER_04]: Why would that... why is that a problem, first of all?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, because the problem is not with the things that arise.
[SPEAKER_02]: Uh-huh.
[SPEAKER_02]: And why that would be is because...
[SPEAKER_05]: But what if... what if they just decide, like, okay, no, I heard that... that the objects are not a problem, so I won't replace them anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, then, you might have the thought that if you have been cultivating the... your view, your attitude, let's say, towards your experience of
[SPEAKER_02]: Getting rid of the stuff that bothers me and getting the stuff that satisfies me is beneficial.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't decide not to have that activity.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have to undo it and it's going to take a while and as soon as you stop
[SPEAKER_02]: That everything that you were doing before was secondary.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And also how dependent on it you are.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, yeah, that's the point, because it's...
[SPEAKER_05]: Because, you know, you might think like, okay, so, obviously, the focusing on objects is wrong, not replacing the one thing with another.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's the basic self-transparency.
[SPEAKER_05]: You realize that's only going to be a temporary solution.
[SPEAKER_05]: But it goes much deeper than just not having heard that right information.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's because even if you get the right information of, oh, I shouldn't be replacing things, I should be enduring them on the right level, quote-unquote,
[SPEAKER_05]: That entire project is going to still be rooted, to some extent, in the fact that you don't want to endure the pressure, because if you allow the pressure to come up...
[SPEAKER_05]: You will do the things that you're used to do on account of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you won't be able to not act out of sensuality and get up and go out, leave you in seclusion, if a real sensual thought were to arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, because you're just not used to...
[SPEAKER_05]: The precepts, that's the point of precepts.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's not a... not a... like, just keeping this external behavior independently of what's going on in your mind.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's like...
[SPEAKER_05]: The whole point of the precept is to train you, so that even if these things arise, you don't act out of them.
[SPEAKER_05]: If you spend most of your day in a state of trance, not even allowing these things to come up, then even if you keep your virtue for 20 years, you haven't trained yourself, because the whole point was to... like, when the mind was aware of these things,
[SPEAKER_05]: Training it not to go for them automatically.
[SPEAKER_05]: And so, only when that's in place, you will be able to train the wild animal, like the elephant, as we put it.
[SPEAKER_04]: You will be able to... because, see, it's like the elephant hasn't even... you haven't even tied it down.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, then, like...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, I was going to say, do you get
[SPEAKER_01]: Even when the person is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: In relation to that citta, which sits behind that, and which is putting the pressure there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if those precepts are not adhered to from the start, you're not even gonna see that mind's pressuring you.
[SPEAKER_04]: And you will still hold the view.
[SPEAKER_04]: Which is quite common, that the whole practice is supposed to prevent the pressure from coming up.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because that's exactly the same thing, the same goal, because of which you act out of sensuality, act out of aversion, because you don't want to have the pressure.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, anything you do,
[SPEAKER_04]: Within that framework, we'll carry that same goal with it.
[SPEAKER_04]: I don't want to hear my mind complaining.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, I would just either give it what it wants, or just put it to sleep.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and so, in the beginning, there's going to be a conflict, in a sense, between you wanting to keep the precepts, and your mind
[SPEAKER_01]: Putting pressure on you, wanting to go the other way.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, there can be a natural inclination saying, look, I do not want to have that inner conflict.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, either you need to be stronger and tame the mind, or you're going to give in to the mind, in order to dissolve the conflict.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, if you give in, in the long run, you'll make it worse.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have no choice but to endure it, so that you become stronger.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, that's pressuring citta, which is always behind you.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's essential to be self-honest about the fact that if you just look at something else and completely forget about that pressure, you're not dealing with the problem, even if temporarily you don't feel the pressure anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the situation of suffering was pressure being present.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, anything that you develop
[SPEAKER_04]: Apart from that setup, it's completely irrelevant to what the problem actually was.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's like, yeah, I can...
[SPEAKER_04]: I can...
[SPEAKER_04]: I don't know, I can...
[SPEAKER_04]: I can run when... when it's not uphill.
[SPEAKER_04]: If it's uphill, I can't do it anymore.
[SPEAKER_04]: And, like, the whole point is, the difficulty was, you couldn't run uphill.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you can be the fastest person in the world running downhill.
[SPEAKER_04]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's the whole idea of meditation today.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's based on that... just developing this huge... piling up this huge set of skills, put on boat.
[SPEAKER_04]: In the domain that's completely separate from the problem that you were met with in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is the relationship between you and your mind, and who's now basically in charge of who.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you just... you're able to do all this stuff and have all this peace and stuff, because the things that provoke the mind are not there anymore.
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, actually, the... like the... the point is... was to take that elephant and tame it, so that it would become a battle elephant, so that even when the... the... it would hear the drums,
[SPEAKER_04]: And people throwing spears at it and stuff.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And see the enemies, armies marching towards it, that it wouldn't run away.
[SPEAKER_04]: That was the whole purpose of taking that elephant out of the forest.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, if now, like, the elephant is tame because nothing's going on,
[SPEAKER_05]: Then, you lost sight of what actually mattered at some point, clearly, because that's what those... that's what pressures are.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's things that are... if the elephant is the citta, then the mind, then that's what these pressures are.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like those... the enemy trying to attack and get the elephant to run away or...
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just... just not do what it's... what you expect to do and put up with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you miss... and you misascribe that, like, factual benefit of, like, the elephant not moving.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or, say, you... you actually go higher up this hill, and you can see further, but it's because you've just been kind of running around, and you happen to climb higher, and you can see further, and you think it's because you've been running around and developing all these skills that you can see further.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And, actually, it was just you... in your... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's...
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, the thing is, no, even then, the things that you would get to see on the basis of wrong samādhi, on the basis of samādhi that's like about blindfolding the elephant and not letting it perceive anything,
[SPEAKER_04]: There is knowledge that can arise out of that, as they would say.
[SPEAKER_04]: Out of wrong samādhi arises wrong knowledge.
[SPEAKER_04]: But the knowledge will be on exactly the same level as the whole samādhi, and exactly on the same level as the whole wrong view of management.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, all of those insights that you would see coming out of this, of that kind of practice of ignoring, which is what meditation is about for most people,
[SPEAKER_04]: It would be about, like, yeah, you would hear, oh, everything is, as we were discussing in that previous talk, like, oh, everything is empty, it doesn't really exist, or it's all constantly changing, or you see the, the kind of, whatever, infinite, whatever, whatever infinite array of views you might come up with,
[SPEAKER_04]: Just to justify yourself or to make yourself feel at ease with that pressure, because you don't want to put up with it.
[SPEAKER_05]: You want to, to some extent, kind of dampen it.
[SPEAKER_05]: You want to decrease it, because you have to convince the elephant.
[SPEAKER_05]: Don't know, actually, that's not the enemy's army.
[SPEAKER_05]: Those are our friends.
[SPEAKER_04]: Just be quiet.
[SPEAKER_04]: Don't move.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because you know that if you just let the elephant
[SPEAKER_04]: Accept the actual reality, without imposing these extra layers of rationalization over it, then it's gonna run.
[SPEAKER_04]: So...
[SPEAKER_04]: In other words, it hasn't been properly trained.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, the right knowledge would come out of that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, when the mind isn't moved,
[SPEAKER_04]: By anything, like, as the sutta would say, even if violent or kind of aggressive sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, not just physical sensations, as people would think, like, I can endure the whatever not sleeping, not eating, not breathing, as the Buddha was doing,
[SPEAKER_05]: No, it's like sights, sounds, smells, thoughts, even, enduring those things on that much more personal level.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's what a tamed mind is able to do.
[SPEAKER_05]: And then, on the basis of those things, you would be able to actually recognize the knowledge that matters, like the Four Noble Truths, which is... None of this was the problem.
[SPEAKER_05]: None of this pressure was the problem.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because now you're able to actually
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, for as long as you're not able to endure it, you won't even be able to direct yourself or to rightly consider the idea that it wasn't the problem.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because the mind will keep constantly kind of putting you on the spot to like, no, no, you have to deal with it, you have to deal with it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Only when it stops and it doesn't care about the pressure anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, that doesn't automatically mean that you will have right knowledge, because some people develop their minds in the suttas without getting the right view.
[SPEAKER_05]: But, if you have the right information and you direct yourself, you direct your mind to that right information, as the suttas would say, of the Four Noble Truths, then you will get to see it, because now it's... now the obstructions that were... like your investment,
[SPEAKER_05]: In wanting to assume that things are otherwise, just so that you can deal with the pressure, now that's gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's nothing preventing you from seeing the obvious nature of like, oh, no, it's actually... it wasn't the sight, sounds, smells, taste, touches, thoughts, phenomena, nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was just my craving in regard to this whole thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, nothing can bother you again once you see that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So...
[SPEAKER_03]: Is there a place for relaxing?
[SPEAKER_03]: In the sense that, if you're so used to trying to manage the situation, whether through just explaining to yourself, like, no, the pressure is not the problem.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, everything that you've discussed and learned, and you don't even
[SPEAKER_03]: You don't need to do that.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're just going to enjoy on.
[SPEAKER_03]: Stop muddling water.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: In a way, it kind of...
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't know, would it be fair to... Relieves the burden.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: It does relieve the burden, but actually, the chitta becomes much more agitated at the same time.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, there is a... maybe on one level, there's a sort of a relaxing, but it's more uncomfortable.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's exactly what I was going to say.
[SPEAKER_05]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: The problem is, when you have the expectation that the realization, the release, the giving up, is supposed to be pleasant immediately, the suttas actually say quite the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: Especially if you haven't been developed in virtue.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha even said like, that which the noble ones regard as pleasant,
[SPEAKER_00]: Ordinary people regard it as a bliss, and vice versa.
[SPEAKER_05]: Like the cessation of... the cessation of everything, like the cessation of your sense of self, cessation of appropriation, cessation of any sense of control that you might have over things, for somebody who's still dependent on that sense of control, and still actively exerts it, and asserts it through their actions,
[SPEAKER_00]: This is going to be like jumping in a pool of cold water, just when you're warm.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it's going to be the complete opposite direction of everything that you're used to.
[SPEAKER_05]: But, from a certain sense, you realize
[SPEAKER_05]: The burden, the burdenlessness of pronunciation, of giving things up, of non-craving, is something that you need to learn to value before it can be pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why some suttas would say that once you've gone forth, the difficult thing is to be content.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, and the other would say, like, the neutral feeling, when you don't understand it, it's going to be unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you understand it, it's going to be peaceful.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, neutral feeling is basically that direction of
[SPEAKER_00]: Giving up of engagements, giving up of concerns, giving up of of involvements, but when the mind is still with the momentum of passion, aversion, and delusion, yeah, it's like when you break a car, it's like, yeah, it's there's that momentum and and it's it's probably, yeah, it's going to start trying to convince you to to keep going.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, that's when you need to hold it back.
[SPEAKER_05]: This is, again, going back to the simile of the elephant.
[SPEAKER_05]: That is the actual purpose of the force of the paṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not for you to just... just ignore the whole thing and enter a different dimension.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's when the mind is pressuring you to continue with that momentum of concerns and passions and involvements.
[SPEAKER_05]: Even if it's not, it's out of the precepts.
[SPEAKER_05]: You tie it down and you refuse to
[SPEAKER_05]: Lose the context of the body, feelings, mind and phenomena.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, these are ways for you to be able to endure the pressure, not ways for you to be able to replace it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why the Buddha would say, yeah, he compared the four satipaṭṭhānas to like the post to which you would tie down the elephant until it calms down.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, far from being an immediately pleasant endeavor, it's actually like an arduous training, which, in a way, he had to keep encouraging monks to be diligent and not
[SPEAKER_00]: Not a relaxer effort, because if it were a matter of just, like, sunshine and vacation from day one, then you wouldn't need an encouragement to do it.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, that same pain... like, it's not a... it's not a torturous pain, like when you're kind of... not the same pain as... as...
[SPEAKER_05]: I don't know... getting your limbs chopped off or something.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's... it's the pain of just having a certain pressure there and not giving in to it, no matter how much... how strongly it arises.
[SPEAKER_00]: That same pressure, if, when you understand it rightly, is where the peace comes from, because you highlight the aspect of, well, this is not right.
[SPEAKER_05]: See, that's the... that's the... that's another thing, like the... as we were saying, why the Buddha wouldn't be teaching... he wouldn't start his training to some random person by saying, oh, nothing is... there's no self, everything is impermanence, by telling them the four noble truths first.
[SPEAKER_05]: He would always begin by saying, first, the clansman hears the teaching and gains faith, he goes forth,
[SPEAKER_05]: Having gone forth, he establishes himself in virtue, then the sense restraint, then all these other things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And at, like, at the last step of his whole training, then he gets to understand the four noble truths, impermanence, the three characteristics, whichever way he wants to approach it, the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because if he were to start with that,
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, telling yourself, oh, this is not mine, as people usually do, or there is no self.
[SPEAKER_05]: You're doing that because you want to get rid of the pressure.
[SPEAKER_05]: In other words, because you're taking it as mine, because you still insist in controlling it, that's why you're telling yourself these things.
[SPEAKER_04]: On the other hand, when you've actually developed yourself, the prerequisites, then, this is not mine, is your way of enduring the pressure.
[SPEAKER_04]: Not your way of running away from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that endurance is pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, like when
[SPEAKER_00]: When you hear about something happening somewhere else, you could have been there, some catastrophe happening, you could have been there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you realize that you weren't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, like, with the natural thing, you would feel the relief.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's the same thing in here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, everything that happens internally, quote-unquote, you're not there with it.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it's like hearing about floods and disasters, but then perpetually realizing that, you know, it's... you're elsewhere.
[SPEAKER_05]: Now, it doesn't mean that you're unaware of it.
[SPEAKER_05]: It doesn't mean that, like, I don't mean that you disappear into a different dimension.
[SPEAKER_05]: Obviously, the five aggregates are still there and there's no outside of it.
[SPEAKER_05]: But, eh... that sense of personal connection, like, as the Buddha would say, whatever feeling he feels, whether pleasant, unpleasant or neutral, he feels it detached or disconnected.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not that you don't feel it, it's that it's felt as disconnected.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, it doesn't bother you.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: But, see, again, you can...
[SPEAKER_04]: Take that on an abstract level of a view before you have developed yourself, and still, your conception of like, oh, it doesn't bother me, would still imply some degree of management.
[SPEAKER_05]: In order to really understand for yourself what it means not to be bothered, you have to develop the mind first, and then see, like, on that proper level of pressure being arisen, and not being moved, not as a matter of choice, because
[SPEAKER_04]: For as long as there's pressure, like the pressure is affecting you, and it's moving you, your choice to try not to be moved would be a way of being moved.
[SPEAKER_05]: There's no way you can escape that.
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, as a matter of choice.
[SPEAKER_05]: Only by developing
[SPEAKER_05]: As the suttas would say, the aggregate of virtue, the proper behavior beforehand, to the point where it doesn't even take effort for you to maintain, and it's there on its own, as the aggregates are.
[SPEAKER_05]: Then, it's like, you would be able to see what it is, see what it means, not to be affected on the right level, without you having to try not to be affected.
[SPEAKER_05]: You recognize, oh, actually,
[SPEAKER_05]: As long as I don't cross this line, which actually takes effort, but I didn't see it because I was used to going over that line, as a beginningless habit, if I don't cross that line, there's nothing that can affect me.
[SPEAKER_03]: You don't even see that management as actually bothersome.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Actually, it's a load.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's like, like, I think I've said it before, it's like Stockholm Syndrome.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's like something that, you know, it's actually painful, but because you're so used to it, even when you get the chance to free yourself from it, which is like perpetually there,
[SPEAKER_04]: You don't want it, because it feels more comfortable to keep doing what you're used to.
[SPEAKER_05]: The immediate safety of just gratifying that desire for pleasure, or gratifying that aversion against pain, trying to get rid of it, that feels kind of...
[SPEAKER_00]: It feels like a guaranteed, immediate reward.
[SPEAKER_05]: Whereas, this is like... you're kind of open to full uncertainty.
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, I can't...
[SPEAKER_05]: I'm not going to control this anymore.
[SPEAKER_05]: But it's a completely different type of
[SPEAKER_05]: There's no ease or peace.
[SPEAKER_05]: You can compare the peace of having your house or whatever always in the perfect temperature, the perfect humidity level, no wind, no insects, whatever, running water.
[SPEAKER_05]: And then, you know, all of that is perpetually subject to all sorts of things that can undermine it.
[SPEAKER_05]: You know, the price of things, the water system breaks down, you have to repair it.
[SPEAKER_05]: And now, compare that with the peace of living on the streets, not caring about whether it's hot, cold, um...
[SPEAKER_05]: It's warm, humid, dry.
[SPEAKER_05]: And you realize, oh, that's... there's basically, even from that mundane perspective, that other type of peace is much more difficult to take away.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because literally, like, it basically doesn't depend on anything.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it's the same with your own mind.
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, the wrong type of peace is when you depend on your own aggregates, on your own senses, on your own internal situation being a certain way.
[SPEAKER_05]: And everything, again, even the right things that the Buddha taught, like not-self and so on,
[SPEAKER_05]: If you're not devout in virtue, you will be using them still to manage that internal environment, to keep the house to the perfect temperature that you prefer.
[SPEAKER_05]: Whereas, it has to come first through you giving up that comfort of management to begin with, and literally going out into the homeless life, internally at least.
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, you know, not trying to manage your own internal home, quote-unquote.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because for as long as you do, you will not be able to understand it is not mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and then the real homelessness is described as seeing the five aggregates as not yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, right.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think there was a sort of...
[SPEAKER_05]: So, that's why it says, whether it's past, present, future, inferior, sublime, coarse or subtle, all form is equally seen as this is not mine, I am not this, this is not myself.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, rather than starting from, again, the standard attitude of management, which is like, I first get the form I want, and then I tell myself that it's not mine,
[SPEAKER_05]: When it's, like, comfortable and easy, eh... no, it's the other way around.
[SPEAKER_05]: You need to take on the uncertainty that any form might arise, any feeling might arise, any perception might arise, because you're not acting out of your gratuitous sense of control anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, factually, anything might happen, and that's how you would understand the true uncertainty, the aggregates, which would then free you from
[SPEAKER_05]: Any suffering that would come on account of them, but at... not for free.
[SPEAKER_05]: Not without the price of giving up the satisfaction of control.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the fear would also be gone, because now it doesn't matter what the advocates do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's no longer a concern.
[SPEAKER_05]: Then you realize, the fear wasn't, same as it was with all the other dharmas, the fear wasn't because of the external things, that, like, I didn't cultivate this kind of...
[SPEAKER_05]: manly attitude of bravery or something.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's always gonna be a way of just managing the aggregates such that they don't become a certain way when you perceive whatever.
[SPEAKER_04]: Whereas, that's not taking you beyond fear.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's like...
[SPEAKER_04]: Same as when you look at, like, a certain food and you try to convince yourself that it's not tasty.
[SPEAKER_04]: As if the lust was the fact that the food was tasty.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_04]: The lust is, when food is tasty, you are lustful towards it.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's what you have to train yourself in regard to.
[SPEAKER_04]: The same as we said before.
[SPEAKER_04]: You have to climb the hill.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, you have to run when it's uphill.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's when the fear is there, when the pressure is there, freeing yourself from that, from any need to act out of that, from any need to manage that and run away from that, that's the true going beyond fear.
[SPEAKER_04]: Not like just...
[SPEAKER_04]: Because, yeah, how many things are there in the world that you could be afraid of?
[SPEAKER_04]: Infinite.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you would never be able to just overcome fear by going through the specific things and toughening up until you can bear all of them.
[SPEAKER_05]: Same with sensuality, same with aversion.
[SPEAKER_05]: You cannot reach metta, like the boundless compassion that the Buddha talked about, by just spreading love towards each individual person or group.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, hoping that they don't become your enemies, so that you then feel at ease.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because, see, it's... again, how many beings exist?
[SPEAKER_04]: How many groups of beings exist that you're not even aware of?
[SPEAKER_04]: So, the fact that you say, may all beings be happy, well...
[SPEAKER_04]: You don't know what all is.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, through that attitude, you will never be able to include everything.
[SPEAKER_04]: Instead, you need to take it on the level of...
[SPEAKER_05]: It doesn't matter how any being makes me feel internally.
[SPEAKER_05]: Same as with the fear.
[SPEAKER_04]: It doesn't matter what any external thing arises in these aggregates.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because you dwell disconnected from the feeling.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: I will not...
[SPEAKER_05]: maintain the assumption of ownership in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, that's why somebody who gives up appropriation of the five aggregates would have automatically developed metta, even if they never heard about that word.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is why we can also perhaps reformulate saying that the right toughening up would be, as you said in the beginning, to start with the virtue.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're not keeping the precepts, but you're
[SPEAKER_00]: I think we said that before, but you're putting up with all sorts of insane physical challenges.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not the right type of development, because...
[SPEAKER_05]: I mean, just think about it.
[SPEAKER_05]: How many people are there in the world who can do difficult things on that physical level, compared to people who are celibate, by choice?
[SPEAKER_05]: Forever.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's, it's, it's... even if it seems like, you know, when people would say the monk's life is just, just a bunch of, bunch of good for nothing.
[SPEAKER_04]: When you sit there, staring at the wall, you realize there's a reason why people don't do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there's plenty of people in the world who just want to get easy food, easy lodgings, easy medicine, and they don't become monks.